Motivation letter

I hereby apply for the two positions "Beschaeftigter mit abgeschl. wiss. Hochschulbildung" (UB-217/17).

I used to work in fundamental research (neuro-genetics). In 2013, the boss of my lab moved to south Germany and let me in charge of the ongoing project, which involved one PhD student and one TA. At the end of the project in 2014, I left the academic race and worked on different projects at the HU, (projects involving an interaction with students and engineers, as well as a practical course organisation). Since then, I gathered more experience in scientific project management, data management and science communication. I am involved in the open science movement and would love to see the linked skills taught to early career researchers. In particular, I think data management should be taught early, not only because it increases the reliability of the research, but also because the scientist will then save an enormous amount of time.

I am looking forward to hear from you, Dr. Julien Colomb

Links:

My website on teaching open science:

https://reproducibleresearch.wordpress.com/

The open science meetup I am running:

http://www.meetup.com/Berlin-Open-Science-Meetup/

Referees:

Prof. Bjoern Brembs, bjoern@brembs.net

Curriculum Vitae

Julien COLOMB, PhD in Biology Schillerpromenade 4 12049 Berlin julien.colomb@fu-berlin.de

 $https://github.com/jcolomb \\ http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520$

Birth: 9 April 1979 in Sion (CH) Married, two children Swiss



Summary

After 12 years spent on fundamental research (neuro-genetics) in which I gathered skills in experimental design, team leading and student teaching, I got most interested in open science and research reproducibility as well as the digital tools helping scientists to achieve it. I then gathered extra experience in business development through the foundation of Drososhare, which turn out not to be sustainable. Since the birth of my second child, i am trying to make a living out of freelance work as data analyst and teaching reproducible research.

Commercial activities

2016-present Freelance scientist (data analysis and project management),

2012-present Founder and CEO of Drososhare GmbH (Berlin, Germany),

Non-commercial activities

2015- present Organisation of the Berlin Open Science meetup:

Discussion on open science themes (Reproducible Research, Open Access, peer

review), and Organisation of the open con satellite conferences

2017- present Part of the march for science Berlin Orga team:

Organisation of a protest in Berlin in 2017 (11000 people came) and further

discussion on future actions

Research activities

2015 - 2016	Postdoctoral fellow, HU & Charité (Berlin, Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
2014 - 2015	Postdoctoral fellow, HU & Charite (Berlin, Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter

2009 -2013 Postdoctoral fellow, FU (**Berlin**, Germany), by Prof. B. Brembs 2007-2008 Postdoctoral fellow, ESPCI (**Paris**, France), by Dr. T. Preat

Education

2016	FELASA B. HU Berlin
2013	Moderation & management (Continuing Education), FU Berlin/Artop.
2006	PhD in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg , Switzerland).
	PhD dissertation: "The chemosensory system of Drosophila larvae: neu-
	roanatomy and behaviour" Thesis director: Prof. R.F Stocker
2002	Diploma in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg, Switzerland)
1998	"Maturité fédérale type C" (scientific subsection), in the "Collège de la royale
	Abbaye de St. Maurice"

Languages

French (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (fluent), Spanish (basics).

Research output

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520 8 research papers (7 first author), 3 reviews, 1 Scienceopen collection https://github.com/jcolomb 3 Open source software (2 main author) h-index =7, Meeting Presentations = 25

Supervision of student

2010-2014	Co-supervisor of the PhD student Christine Damrau (with Dr. B.Brembs) on
2008	the role of octopamine in reward, motivation and motor control in <i>Drosophila</i> . Co-supervisor of the PhD student Séverine Trannoy (with Dr. G. Isabel and
	Dr. N. Gervasi) on the role of dopamine in appetitive learning consolidation in
	Drosophila.
2005	Co-supervisor of the diploma work of Claire Huguenin (with Dr. A. Ramaekers)
	on the role of NO in olfactory discrimination in <i>Drosophila</i> larvae.

Teaching experience

2016	Animal models of neuropathy, (master student, 2x2h lecture, organisation)
2012	Genetik (bachelor student, 2 x 3 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar)
2012	Neurogenetik. (master student, 2 x 2 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar)
2011	Practical course neurobiology. (7 x 4 h., Practical course supervision)
2011	Entwicklung der Insekten [Insect development] (2 h. lecture)
2006	Fluorescence and Confocal Microscopy (master student, 3h. lecture)
2003-2006	Studying behavior. (master student, 2 h. lecture)
2003-2005	Developmental- and Neurogenetics (master student, 2 h. lecture).

Computer skills

Organisation and publication: OSX, Windows, Outlook, Access; , LATEX, Office; html; Image processing and scientific platform: Photoshop, Illustrator, Image J, Inscape; labfolder, figshare, github, overleaf, authorea, scienceopen Programming: R (advanced), Git, Labview

Other tasks

Creation of the T. Preat's and R.F. Stocker's lab website. Co-director in the theater group "les apostrophes" in 2006